APPENDIX

CORRESPONDENCE OF M. AURELIUS ANTONINUS AND M. CORNELIUS FRONTO[1]

M. CORNELIUS FRONTO was a Roman by descent, but of provincial birth, being native to Cirta, in Numidia. Thence he migrated to Rome in the reign of Hadrian, and became the most famous rhetorician of his day. As a pleader and orator he was counted by his contemporaries hardly inferior to Tully himself, and as a teacher his aid was sought for the noblest youths of Rome. To him was entrusted the education of M.

Aurelius and of his colleague L. Verus in their boyhood; and he was rewarded for his efforts by a seat in the Senate and the consular rank (A.D. 143). By the exercise of his profession he became wealthy; and if he speaks of his means as not great,[2] he must be comparing his wealth with the grandees of Rome, not with the ordinary citizen.

Before the present century nothing was known of the works of Fronto, except a grammatical treatise; but in 1815 Cardinal Mai published a number of letters and some short essays of Fronto, which he had discovered in a palimpsest at Milan. Other parts of the same MS. he found later in the Vatican, the whole being collected

[1] References are made to the edition of Naber, Leipzig (Trübner), 1867.

[2] Ad Verum imp. Aur. Caes., ii, 7. and edited in the year 1823.

We now possess parts of his correspondence with Antoninus Pius, with M. Aurelius, with L. Verus, and with certain of his friends, and also several rhetorical and historical fragments. Though none of the more ambitious works of Fronto have survived, there are enough to give proof of his powers. Never was a great literary reputation less deserved. It would be hard to conceive of anything more vapid than the style and conception of these letters; clearly the man was a pedant without imagination or taste. Such indeed was the age he lived in, and it is no marvel that he was like to his age. But there must have been more in him than mere pedantry; there was indeed a heart in the man, which Marcus found, and he found also a tongue which could speak the truth. Fronto's letters are by no means free from exaggeration and laudation, but they do not show that loathsome flattery which filled the Roman court. He really admires what he praises, and his way of saying so is not unlike what often passes for criticism at the present day. He is not afraid to reprove what he thinks amiss; and the astonishment of Marcus at this will prove, if proof were needed, that he was not used to plain dealing. "How happy I am," he writes, "that my friend Marcus Cornelius, so distinguished as an orator and so noble as a man, thinks me worth praising and blaming."[3] In another place he deems himself blest because Pronto had taught him to speak the truth[4] although the context shows him to be speaking of expression, it is still a point in favour of Pronto. A sincere heart is better than literary taste; and if Fronto had not done his duty by the young prince, it is not easy to understand the friendship which remained between them up to the last.

[3] Ad M. Caes iii. 17

[4] Ad M. Caes iii. 12

An example of the frankness which was between them is given by a difference they had over the case of Herodes Atticus. Herodes was a Greek rhetorician who had a school at Rome, and Marcus Aurelius was among his pupils. Both Marcus and the Emperor Antoninus had a high opinion of Herodes; and all we know goes to prove he was a man of high character and princely generosity. When quite young he was made administrator of the free cities in Asia, nor is it surprising to find that he made bitter enemies there; indeed, a just ruler was sure to make enemies. The end of it was that an Athenian deputation, headed by the orators Theodotus and Demostratus, made serious accusations against his honour. There is no need to discuss the merits of the case here; suffice it to say, Herodes succeeded in defending himself to the satisfaction of the emperor. Pronto appears to have taken the delegates' part, and to have accepted a brief for the prosecution, urged to some extent by personal considerations; and in this cause Marcus Aurelius writes to Fronto as follows:—

'AURELIUS CÆSAR to his friend FRONTO, greeting.[5]

'I know you have often told me you were anxious to find how you might best please me. Now is the time; now you can increase my love towards you, if it can be increased. A trial is at hand, in which people seem likely not only to hear your speech with pleasure, but to see your indignation with impatience. I see no one who dares give you a hint in the matter; for those who are less friendly, prefer to see you act with some inconsistency; and those who are more friendly, fear to seem too friendly to your opponent if they should dissuade you from your accusation; then again, in case you have prepared something neat for the occasion, they cannot endure to rob you of your harangue by silencing you. Therefore, whether you think me a rash counsellor, or a bold boy, or too kind to your opponent, not because I think it better, I will offer my counsel with some caution. But why have I said, offer my counsel? No, I demand it from you; I demand it boldly, and if I succeed, I promise to remain under your obligation. What? you will say if I am attackt, shall I not pay tit for tat? Ah, but you will get greater glory, if even when attackt you answer nothing. Indeed, if he begins it, answer as you will and you will have fair excuse; but I have demanded of him that he shall not begin, and I think I have succeeded. I love each of you according to your merits and I know that lie was educated in the house of P. Calvisius, my grandfather, and that I was educated by you; therefore I am full of anxiety that this most disagreeable business shall be managed as honourably as possible. I trust you may approve my advice, for my intention you will approve. At least I prefer to write unwisely rather than to be silent unkindly.'

[5] Ad M. Caes ii., 2.

Fronto replied, thanking the prince for his advice, and promising that he will confine himself to the facts of the case. But he points out that the charges brought against Herodes were such, that they can hardly be made agreeable; amongst them being spoliation, violence, and murder. However, he is willing even to let some of these drop if it be the prince's pleasure. To this Marcus returned the following answer:—[6] 'This one thing, my dearest Fronto, is enough to make me truly grateful to you, that so far from rejecting my counsel, you have even approved it. As to the question you raise in your kind letter, my opinion is this: all that concerns the case which you are supporting must be clearly brought forward; what concerns your own feelings, though you may have had just provocation, should be left unsaid.' The story does credit to both. Fronto shows no loss of temper at the interference, nor shrinks from stating his case with frankness; and Marcus, with forbearance remarkable in a prince, does not command that his friend be left unmolested, but merely stipulates for a fair trial on the merits of the case.

[6] Ad. M. Caes., iii. 5.

Another example may be given from a letter of Fronto's[7] Here is something else quarrelsome and querulous. I have sometimes found fault with you in your absence somewhat seriously in the company of a few of my most intimate friends: at times, for example, when you mixt in society with a more solemn look than was fitting, or would read books in the theatre or in a banquet; nor did I absent myself from theatre or banquet when you did.[8] Then I used to call you a hard man, no good company, even disagreeable, sometimes, when anger got the better of me. But did any one else in the same banquet speak against you, I could not endure to hear it with equanimity. Thus it was easier for me to say something to your disadvantage myself, than to hear others do it; just as I could more easily bear to chastise my daughter Gratia, than to see her chastised by another.'

[7] Ad. M. Caes., iv. 12.

[8] The text is obscure

The affection between them is clear from every page of the correspondence. A few instances are now given, which were written at different periods

To MY MASTER.[9]

'This is how I have past the last few days. My sister was suddenly seized with an internal pain, so violent that I was horrified at her looks; my mother in her trepidation on that account accidentally bruised her side on a corner of the wall; she and we were greatly troubled about that blow. For myself; on going to rest I found a scorpion in my bed; but I did not lie down upon him, I killed him first. If you are getting on better, that is a consolation. My mother is easier now, thanks be to God. Good-bye, best and sweetest master. My lady sends you greeting.'

[9] Ad M. Caes., v. 8.

[10]'What words can I find to fit my had luck, or how shall I upbraid as it deserves the hard constraint which is laid upon me? It ties me fast here, troubled my heart is, and beset by such anxiety; nor does it allow me to make haste to my Fronto, my life and delight, to be near him at such a moment of ill-health in particular, to hold his hands, to chafe gently that identical foot, so far as may be done without discomfort, to attend him in the bath, to support his steps with my arm.'

[10] Ad M. Caes., i. 2.

[11]'This morning I did not write to you, because I heard you were better, and because I was myself engaged in other business, and I cannot ever endure to write anything to you unless with mind at ease and untroubled and free. So if we are all right, let me know: what I desire, you know, and how properly I desire it, I know. Farewell, my master, always in every chance first in my mind, as you deserve to be. My master, see I am not asleep, and I compel myself to sleep, that you may not be angry with me. You gather I am writing this late at night.'

[11] iii. 21.

[12]'What spirit do you suppose is in me, when I remember how long it is since I have seen you, and why I have not seen you! and it may be I shall not see you for a few days yet, while you are strengthening yourself; as you must. So while you lie on the sick-bed, my spirit also will lie low anti, whenas,[13] by God's mercy you shall stand upright, my spirit too will stand firm, which is now burning with the strongest desire for you. Farewell, soul of your prince, your pupil.'

[14]O my dear Fronto, most distinguished Consul! I yield, you have conquered: all who have ever loved before, you have conquered out and out in love's contest. Receive the victor's wreath; and the herald shall proclaim your victory aloud before your own tribunal: "M. Cornelius Fronto, Consul, wins, and is crowned victor in the Open International Love-race."[15] But beaten though I may be, I shall neither slacken nor relax my own zeal. Well, you shall love me more than any man loves any other man; but I, who possess a faculty of loving less strong, shall love you more than any one else loves you; more indeed than you love yourself. Gratia and I will have to fight for it; I doubt I shall not get the better of her. For, as Plautus says, her love is like rain, whose big drops not only penetrate the dress, but drench to the very marrow.'

[12] Ad M. Caes., iii. 19.

[13] The writer sometimes uses archaisms such as quom, which I render 'whenas'.

[14] Ad M. Caes., ii. 2.

[15] The writer parodies the proclamation at the Greek games; the words also are Greek.

Marcus Aurelius seems to have been about eighteen years of age when the correspondence begins, Fronto being some thirty years older.[16] The systematic education of the young prince seems to have been finisht, and Pronto now acts more as his adviser than his tutor. He recommends the prince to use simplicity in his public speeches, and to avoid affectation.[17] Marcus devotes his attention to the old authors who then had a great vogue at Rome: Ennius, Plautus, Nævius, and such orators as Cato and Gracchus.[18] Pronto urges on him the study of Cicero, whose letters, he says, are all worth reading.

[16] From internal evidence: the letters are not arranged in order of time. See Naher's Prolegomena, p. xx. foll.

[17] Ad M. Caes., iii. x.

[18] Ad M. Caes ii. 10,; iii. 18,; ii. 4.

When he wishes to compliment Marcus he declares one or other of his letters has the true Tullian ring. Marcus gives his nights to reading when he ought to be sleeping. He exercises himself in verse composition and on rhetorical themes.

'It is very nice of you,' he writes to Fronto,[19] 'to ask for my hexameters; I would have sent them at once if I had them by me. The fact is my secretary, Anicetus-you know who I mean-did not pack up any of my compositions for me to take away with me. He knows my weakness; he was afraid that if I got hold of them I might, as usual, make smoke of them. However, there was no fear for the hexameters. I must confess the truth to my master: I love them. I study at night, since the day is taken up with the theatre. I am weary of an evening, and sleepy in the daylight, and so I don't do much. Yet I have made extracts from sixty books, five volumes of them, in these latter days. But when you read remember that the "sixty" includes plays of Novius, and farces, and some little speeches of Scipio; don't be too much startled at the number. You remember your Polemon; but I pray you do not remember Horace, who has died with Pollio as far as I am concerned.[20] Farewell, my dearest and most affectionate friend, most distinguished consul and my beloved master, whom I have not seen these two years. Those who say two months, count the days. Shall I ever see you again?'

[19] Ad M. Caes., ii. 10.

[20] He implies, as in i. 6, that he has ceased to study Horace.

Sometimes Fronto sends him a theme to work up, as thus: 'M. Lucilius tribune of the people violently throws into prison a free Roman citizen, against the opinion of his colleagues who demand his release. For this act he is branded by the censor. Analyse the case, and then take both sides in turn, attacking and defending.'[21] Or again: 'A Roman consul, doffing his state robe, dons the gauntlet and kills a lion amongst the young men at the Quinquatrus in full view of the people of Rome. Denunciation before the censors.'[22] The prince has a fair knowledge of Greek, and quotes from Homer, Plato, Euripides, but for some reason Fronto dissuaded him from this study.[23] His Meditations are written in Greek. He continued his literary studies throughout his life, and after he became emperor we still find him asking his adviser for copies of Cicero's Letters, by which he hopes to improve his vocabulary.[24] Pronto helps him with a supply of similes, which, it seems, he did not think of readily. It is to be feared that the fount of Marcus's eloquence was pumped up by artificial means.

[21] Pollio was a grammarian, who taught Marcus.

[22] Ad M. Caes., v. 27,; V. 22.

[23] Ep. Gracae, 6.

[24] Ad Anton. Imp., II. 4.

Some idea of his literary style may be gathered from the letter which follows:[25]

'I heard Polemo declaim the other day, to say something of things sublunary. If you ask what I thought of him, listen. He seems to me an industrious farmer, endowed with the greatest skill, who has cultivated a large estate for corn and vines only, and indeed with a rich return of fine crops. But yet in that land of his there is no Pompeian fig or Arician vegetable, no Tarentine rose, or pleasing coppice, or thick grove, or shady plane tree; all is for use rather than for pleasure, such as one ought rather to commend, but cares not to love.

[25] Ad M. Caes, ii. 5.

A pretty bold idea, is it not, and rash judgment, to pass censure on a man of such reputation? But whenas I remember that I am writing to you, I think I am less bold than you would have me.

'In that point I am wholly undecided.

'There's an unpremeditated hendecasyllable for you. So before I begin to poetize, I'll take an easy with you. Farewell, my heart's desire, your Verus's best beloved, most distinguisht consul, master most sweet. Farewell I ever pray, sweetest soul.

What a letter do you think you have written me I could make bold to say, that never did she who bore me and nurst me, write anything SO delightful, so honey-sweet. And this does not come of your fine style and eloquence: otherwise not my mother only, but all who breathe.'

To the pupil, never was anything on earth so fine as his master's eloquence; on this theme Marcus fairly bubbles over with enthusiasm.

[26]'Well, if the ancient Greeks ever wrote anything like this, let those who know decide it: for me, if I dare say so, I never read any invective of Cato's so fine as your encomtum. O if my Lord[27] could be sufficiently praised, sufficiently praised he would have been undoubtedly by you! This kind of thing is not done nowadays.[28] It were easier to match Pheidias, easier to match Apelles, easier in a word to match Demosthenes himself, or Cato himself; than to match this finisht and perfect work. Never have I read anything more refined, anything more after the ancient type, anything more delicious, anything more Latin. O happy you, to be endowed with eloquence so great! O happy I, to be tinder the charge of such a master! O arguments,[29] O arrangement, O elegance, O wit, O beauty, O words, O brilliancy, O subtilty, O grace, O treatment, O everything! Mischief take me, if you ought not to have a rod put in your hand one day, a diadem on your brow, a tribunal raised for you; then the herald would summon us all-why do I say "us"? Would summnon all, those scholars and orators: one by one you would beckon them forward with your rod and admonish them. Hitherto I have had no fear of this admonition; many things help me to enter within your school. I write this in the utmost haste; for whenas I am sending you so kindly a letter from my Lord, what needs a longer letter of mine? Farewell then, glory of Roman eloquence, boast of your friends, magnifico, most delightful man, most distinguished consul, master most sweet.

[26] Ad M. Caes., ii. 3.

[27] The Emperor Antoninus Pius is spoken of as dominus meus.

[28] This sentence is written in Greek.

[29] Several of these words are Greek, and the meaning is not quite clear.

'After this you will take care not to tell so many fibs of me, especially in the Senate. A monstrous fine speech this is! O if I could kiss your head at every heading of it! You have looked down on all with a vengeance. This oration once read, in vain shall we study, in vain shall we toil, in vain strain every nerve. Farewell always, most sweet master.'

Sometimes Fronto descends from the heights of eloquence to offer practical advice; as when he suggests how Marcus should deal with his suite. It is more difficult, he admits, to keep courtiers in harmony than to tame lions with a lute; but if it is to be done, it must be by eradicating jealousy. 'Do not let your friends,' says Fronto,'[30] 'envy each other, or think that what you give to another is filched from them.

[30] Ad M Caes., iv. 1.

Keep away envy from your suite, and you will find your friends kindly and harmonious.'

Here and there we meet with allusions to his daily life, which we could wish to be more frequent. He goes to the theatre or the law-courts,[31] or takes part in court ceremony, but his heart is always with his books. The vintage season, with its religious rites, was always spent by Antoninus Pius in the country. The following letters give sonic notion of a day's occupation at that time:[32]

[31] ii. 14

[32] iv. 5,6.

'MY DEAREST MASTER,—I am well. To-day I studied from the ninth hour of the night to the second hour of day, after taking food. I then put on my slippers, and from time second to the third hour had a most enjoyable walk up and down before my chamber. Then booted and cloaked-for so we were commanded to appear-I went to wait upon my lord the emperor. We went a-hunting, did doughty deeds, heard a rumour that boars had been caught, but there was nothing to see. However, we climbed a pretty steep hill, and in the afternoon returned home. I went straight to my books. Off with the boots, down with the cloak; I spent a couple of hours in bed. I read Cato's speech on the Property of Pulchra, and another in which he impeaches a tribune. Ho, ho! I hear you cry to your man, Off with you as fast as you can, and bring me these speeches from the library of Apollo. No use to send: I have those books with me too. You must get round the Tiberian librarian; you will have to spend something on the matter; and when I return to town, I shall expect to go shares with him. Well, after reading these speeches I wrote a wretched trifle, destined for drowning or burning. No, indeed my attempt at writing did not come off at all to-day; the composition of a hunter or a vintager, whose shouts are echoing through my chamber, hateful and wearisome as the law-courts. What have I said? Yes, it was rightly said, for my master is an orator. I think I have caught cold, whether from walking in slippers or from writing badly, I do not know. I am always annoyed with phlegm, but to-day I seem to snivel more than usual. Well, I will pour oil on my head and go off to sleep. I don't mean to put one drop in my lamp to-day, so weary am I from riding and sneezing. Farewell, dearest and most beloved master, whom I miss, I may say, more than Rome itself.'

'MY BELOVED MASTER,-I am well. I slept a little more than usual for my slight cold, which seems to be well again. So I spent the time from the eleventh hour of the night to the third of the day partly in reading in Cato's Agriculture, partly in writing, not quite so badly as yesterday indeed. Then, after waiting upon my father, I soothed my throat with honey-water, ejecting it without swallowing: I might say gargle, but I won't, though I think the word is found in Novius and elsewhere. After attending to my throat I went to my father, and stood by his side as he sacrificed. Then to luncheon. What do you think I had to eat? A bit of bread so big, while I watched others gobbling boiled beans, onions, and fish full of roe. Then we set to work at gathering the grapes, with plenty of sweat and shouting, and, as the quotation runs, "A few high-hanging clusters did we leave survivors of the vintage." After the sixth hour we returned home. I did a little work, and poor work at that. Then I had a long gossip with my dear mother sitting on the bed. My conversation was: What do you think my friend Fronto is doing just now? She said: And what do you think of my friend Gratia?'[33] My turn now: And what of our little Gratia,[34] the sparrowkin? After this kind of talk, and an argument as to which of you loved the other most, the gong sounded, the signal that my father had gone to the bath. We supped, after ablutions in the oil-cellar-I mean we supped after ablutions, not after ablutions in the oil-cellar; and listened with enjoyment to the rustics gibing. After returning, before turning on my side to snore, I do my task and give an account of the day to my delightful master, whom if I could long for a little more, I should not mind growing a trifle thinner. Farewell, Fronto, wherever you are, honey-sweet, my darling, my delight. Why do I want you? I can love you while far away.'

[33] Fronto's wife.

[34] Fronto's daughter

One anecdote puts Marcus before us in a new light:[35]

[35] Ad M. Caes ii. 12.

'When my father returned home from the vineyards, I mounted my horse as usual, and rode on ahead some little way. Well, there on the road was a herd of sheep, standing all crowded together as though the place were a desert, with four dogs and two shepherds, but nothing else. Then one shepherd said to another shepherd, on seeing a number of horsemen: 'I say,' says he, 'look you at those horsemen; they do a deal of robbery.' When I heard this, I clap spurs to my horse, and ride straight for the sheep. In consternation the sheep scatter; hither and thither they are fleeting and bleating. A shepherd throws his fork, and the fork falls on the horseman who came next to me. We make our escape.' We like Marcus none the worse for this spice of mischief.

Another letter[36] describes a visit to a country town, and shows the antiquarian spirit of the writer:—

'M. CÆSAR to his MASTER M. FRONTO, greeting.

'After I entered the carriage, after I took leave of you, we made a journey comfortable enough, but we had a few drops of rain to wet us. But before coming to the country-house, we broke our journey at Anagnia, a mile or so from the highroad. Then we inspected that ancient town, a miniature it is, but has in it many antiquities, temples, and religious ceremonies quite out of the way. There is not a corner without its shrine, or fane, or temple; besides, many books written on linen, which belongs to things sacred. Then on the gate as we came out was written twice, as follows: "Priest don the fell."[37] I asked one of the inhabitants what that word was. He said it was the word in the Hernican dialect for the victim's skin, which the priest puts over his conical cap when he enters the city. I found out many other things which I desired to know, but the only thing I do not desire is that you should be absent from me; that is my chief anxiety. Now for yourself, when you left that place, did you go to Aurelia or to Campania? Be sure to write to me, and say whether you have opened the vintage, or carried a host of books to the country-house; this also, whether you miss me; I am foolish to ask it, whenas you tell it me of yourself. Now if you miss me and if you love me, send me your letters often, which is a comfort and consolation to me. Indeed I should prefer ten times to read your letters than all the vines of Gaurus or the Marsians; for these Signian vines have grapes too rank and fruit too sharp in the taste, but I prefer wine to must for drinking. Besides, those grapes are nicer to eat dried than fresh-ripe; I vow I would rather tread them under foot than put my teeth in them. But I pray they may be gracious and forgiving, and grant me free pardon for these jests of mine. Farewell, best friend, dearest, most learned, sweetest master. When you see the must ferment in the vat, remember that just so in my heart the longing for you is gushing and flowing and bubbling. Good-bye.'

[36] Ad Verum. Imp ii. 1, s. fin.

[37] Santentum

Making all allowances for conventional exaggerations, it is clear from the correspondence that there was deep love between Marcus and his preceptor. The letters cover several years in succession, but soon after the birth of Marcus's daughter, Faustina, there is a large gap. It does not follow that the letters ceased entirely, because we know part of the collection is lost; but there was probably less intercourse between Marcus and Fronto after Marcus took to the study of philosophy under the guidance of Rusticus.

When Marcus succeeded to the throne in 161, the letters begin again, with slightly increased formality on Fronto's part, and they go on for some four years, when Fronto, who has been continually complaining of ill-health, appears to have died. One letter of the later period gives some interesting particulars of the emperor's public life, which are worth quoting. Fronto speaks of Marcus's victories and eloquence in the usual strain of high praise, and then continues.[38]

'The army when you took it in hand was sunk in luxury and revelry, and corrupted with long inactivity. At Antiochia the soldiers had been Wont to applaud at the stage plays, knew more of the gardens at the nearest restaurant than of the battlefield. Horses were hairy from lack of grooming, horsemen smooth because their hairs had been pulled out by the roots[39] a rare thing it was to see a soldier with hair on arm or leg. Moreover, they were better drest than armed; so much so, that Laelianus Pontius, a strict man of the old discipline, broke the cuirasses of some of them with his finger-tips, and observed cushions on the horses' backs. At his direction the tufts were cut through, and out of the horsemen's saddles came what appeared to be feathers pluckt from geese. Few of the men could vault on horseback, the rest clambered up with difficulty by aid of heel and knee and leg not many could throw a lance hurtling, most did it without force or power, as though they were things of wool-dicing was common in the camp, sleep lasted all night, or if they kept watch it was over the winecup. By what regulations to restrain such soldiers as these, and to turn them to honesty and industry, did you not learn from Hannibal's sternness, the discipline of Africanus, the acts of Metellus recorded in history.

[38] Ad Verum. imp., ii. I, s.fin.

[39] A common mark of the effeminate at Rome.

After the preceptorial letters cease the others are concerned with domestic events, health and sickness, visits or introductions, birth or death. Thus the empperor writes to his old friend, who had shown some diffidence in seeking an interview:[40]

[40] Ad Verum. Imp. Aur. Caes., i. 3.

'To MY MASTER.

'I have a serious grievance against you, my dear master, yet indeed my grief is more than my grievance, because after so long a time I neither embraced you nor spoke to you, though you visited the palace, and the moment after I had left the prince my brother. I reproached my brother severely for not recalling me; nor durst he deny the fault.' Fronto again writes on one occasion: 'I have seen your daughter. It was like seeing you and Faustina in infancy, so much that is charming her face has taken from each of yours.' Or again, at a later date:[41] I have seen your chicks, most delightful sight that ever I saw in my life, so like you that nothing is more like than the likeness.... By the mercy of Heaven they have a healthy colour and strong lungs. One held a piece of white bread, like a little prince, the other a common piece, like a true philosophers son.'

[41] Ad Ant. Imp i., 3.

Marcus, we know, was devoted to his children. They were delicate in health, in spite of Fronto's assurance, and only one son survived the father. We find echoes of this affection now and again in the letters. 'We have summer heat here still,' writes Marcus, 'but since my little girls are pretty well, if I may say so, it is like the bracing climate of spring to us.'[42] When little Faustina came back from the valley of the shadow of death, her father at once writes to inform Fronto.[43] The sympathy he asks he also gives, and as old age brings more and more infirmity, Marcus becomes even more solicitous for his beloved teacher. The poor old man suffered a heavy blow in the death of his grandson, on which Marcus writes:[44] 'I have just heard of your misfortune. Feeling grieved as I do when one of your joints gives you pain, what do you think I feel, dear master, when you have pain of mind?' The old man's reply, in spite of a certain self-consciousness, is full of pathos. He recounts with pride the events of a long and upright life, in which he has wronged no man, and lived in harmony with his friends and family. His affectations fall away from him, as the cry of pain is forced from his heart:—

[42] Ad M. Caes., v. 19

[43] iv. 11

[44] De Nepote Amissa

[45]'Many such sorrows has fortune visited me with all my life long. To pass by my other afflictions, I have lost five children under the most pitiful conditions possible: for the five I lost one by one when each was my only child, suffering these blows of bereavement in such a manner that each child was born to one already bereaved. Thus I ever lost my children without solace, and got them amidst fresh grief.....'

[45] De Nepote Amissa 2

The letter continues with reflections on the nature of death, 'more to be rejoiced at than bewailed, the younger one dies,' and an arraignment of Providence not without dignity, wrung from him as it were by this last culminating misfortune. It concludes with a summing-up of his life in protest against the blow which has fallen on his grey head.

'Through my long life I have committed nothing which might bring dishonour, or disgrace, or shame: no deed of avarice or treachery have I done in all my day's: nay, but much generosity, much kindness, much truth and faithfulness have I shown, often at the risk of my own life. I have lived in amity with my good brother, whom I rejoice to see in possession of the highest office by your father's goodness, and by your friendship at peace and perfect rest. The offices which I have myself obtained I never strove for by any underhand means. I have cultivated my mind rather than my body; the pursuit of learning I have preferred to increasing my wealth. I preferred to be poor rather than bound by any' man's obligation, even to want rather than to beg. I have never been extravagant in spending money, I have earned it sometimes because I must. I have scrupulously spoken the truth, and have been glad to hear it spoken to me. I have thought it better to be neglected than to fawn, to be dumb than to feign, to be seldom a friend than to be often a flatterer. I have sought little, deserved not little. So far as I could, I have assisted each according to my means. I have given help readily to the deserving, fearlessly to the undeserving. No one by proving to be ungrateful has made me more slow to bestow promptly all benefits I could give, nor have I ever been harsh to ingratitude. (A fragmentary passage follows, in which he appears to speak of his desire for a peaceful end, and the desolation of his house.) I have suffered long and painful sickness, my beloved Marcus. Then I was visited by pitiful misfortunes: my wife I have lost, my grandson I have lost in Germany:[46] woe is me! I have lost my Decimanus. If I were made of iron, at this tine I could write no more.'

[46] In the war against the Catti.

It is noteworthy that in his Meditations Marcus Aurelius mentions Fronto only once.[47] All his literary studies, his oratory and criticism (such as it was) is forgotten; and, says he, 'Fronto taught me not to expect natural affection from the highly-born.' Fronto really said more than this: that 'affection' is not a Roman quality, nor has it a Latin name.[48] Roman or not Roman, Marcus found affection in Fronto; and if he outgrew his master's intellectual training, he never lost touch with the true heart of the man it is that which Fronto's name brings up to his remembrance, not dissertations on compound verbs or fatuous criticisms of style.

[47] Book I., 8.

[48] Ad Verum, ii. 7

NOTES

This being neither a critical edition of the text nor an emended edition of Casaubon's translation, it has not been thought necessary to add full notes. Casaubon's own notes have been omitted, because for the most part they are discursive, and not necessary to an understanding of what is written. In those which here follow, certain emendations of his are mentioned, which he proposes in his notes, and follows in the translation. In addition, one or two corrections are made where he has mistaken the Greek, and the translation might be misleading. Those which do not come under these two heads will explain themselves.

The text itself has been prepared by a comparison of the editions of 1634 and 1635. It should be borne in mind that Casaubon's is often rather a paraphrase than a close translation; and it did not seem worth while to notice every variation or amplification of the original. In the original editions all that Casaubon conceives as understood, but not expressed, is enclosed in square brackets. These brackets are here omitted, as they interfere with the comfort of the reader; and so have some of the alternative renderings suggested by the translator. In a few cases, Latin words in the text have been replaced by English.

Numbers in brackets refer to the Teubner text of Stich, but the divisions of the text are left unaltered. For some of the references identified I am indebted to Mr. G. H. Rendall's Marcus Aurelius.

BOOK II "Both to frequent" (4). Gr. τὸ μή, C. conjectures τὸ μὲ. The text is probably right: "I did not frequent public lectures, and I was taught at home."

VI Idiots.... philosophers (9). The reading is doubtful, but the meaning seems to be: "simple and unlearned men"

XII "Claudius Maximus" (15). The reading of the Palatine MS. (now lost) was paraklhsiz Maximon, which C. supposes to conceal the letters kl as an abbreviation of Claudius.

XIII "Patient hearing... He would not" (16). C. translates his conjectural reading epimonon ollan. on proapsth Stich suggests a reading with much the same sense: .....epimonon all antoi "Strict and rigid dealing" (16). C. translates tonvn (Pal. MS.) as though from tonoz, in the sense of "strain." "rigour." The reading of other MSS. tonvn is preferable.

XIII "Congiaries" (13). dianomais, "doles."

XIV "Cajeta" (17). The passage is certainly corrupt. C. spies a reference to Chryses praying by the sea-shore in the Illiad, and supposes M. Aurelius to have done the like. None of the emendations suggested is satisfactory. At § XV. Book II. is usually reckoned to begin. BOOK II III. "Do, soul" (6). If the received reading be right, it must be sarcastic; but there are several variants which show how unsatisfactory it is. C. translates "en gar o bioz ekasty so par eanty", which I do not understand. The sense required is: "Do not violence to thyself, for thou hast not long to use self-respect. Life is not (v. 1. so long for each, and this life for thee is all but done."

X. "honour and credit do proceed" (12). The verb has dropt out of the text, but C. has supplied one of the required meaning.

XI. "Consider," etc. (52). This verb is not in the Greek, which means: "(And reason also shows) how man, etc."

BOOK IV XV. "Agathos" (18): This is probably not a proper name, but the text seems to be unsound. The meaning may be "the good man ought"

XVI. oikonomian (16) is a "practical benefit," a secondary end. XXXIX. "For herein lieth all...." (~3). C. translates his conjecture olan for ola.

BOOK V XIV. katorqwseiz (15): Acts of "rightness" or "straightness." XXIII. "Roarer" (28): Gr. "tragedian." Ed. 1 has whoremonger,' ed. 2 corrects to "harlot," but omits to alter' the word at its second occurrence.

XXV. "Thou hast... them" (33): A quotation from Homer, Odyssey, iv. 690.

XXVII. "One of the poets" (33): Hesiod, Op. et Dies, 197.

XXIX and XXX. (36). The Greek appears to contain quotations from sources not known, and the translation is a paraphrase. (One or two alterations are here made on the authority of the second edition.) BOOK VI XIII. "Affected and qualified" (i4): exis, the power of cohesion shown in things inanimate; fusiz, power of growth seen in plants and the like.

XVII. "Wonder at them" (18): i.e. mankind.

XXXVII. "Chrysippus" (42): C. refers to a passage of Plutarch De Communibus Notitiis (c. xiv.), where Chrysippus is represented as saying that a coarse phrase may be vile in itself, yet have due place in a comedy as contributing to a certain effect.

XL. "Man or men..." There is no hiatus in the Greek, which means: "Whatever (is beneficial) for a man is so for other men also."

XLII. There is no hiatus in the Greek.

BOOK VII IX. C. translates his conjecture mh for h. The Greek means "straight, or rectified," with a play on the literal and metaphorical meaning of ortoz.

XIV. endaimonia. contains the word daimwn in composition. XXII. The text is corrupt, but the words "or if it be but few" should be "that is little enough."

XXIII. "Plato": Republic, vi. p. 486 A.

XXV. "It will," etc. Euripides, Belerophon, frag. 287 (Nauck).

"Lives," etc. Euripides, Hypsipyle, frag. 757 (Nauck). "As long," etc. Aristophanes, Acharne, 66 i.

"Plato" Apology, p. 28 B.

"For thus" Apology, p. 28 F.

XXVI. "But, O noble sir," etc. Plato, Gorgias, 512 D. XXVII. "And as for those parts," etc. A quotation from Euripides, Chryssipus, frag. 839 (Nauck).

"With meats," etc. From Euripides, Supplices, 1110. XXXIII. "They both," i.e. life and wrestling.

"Says he" (63): Plato, quoted by Epictetus, Arr. i. 28, 2 and 22.

XXXVII. "How know we," etc. The Greek means: "how know we whether Telauges were not nobler in character than Sophocles?" The allusion is unknown.

XXVII. "Frost" The word is written by Casaubon as a proper name, "Pagus.'

"The hardihood of Socrates was famous"; see Plato, Siymposium, p. 220.

BOOK X XXII. The Greek means, "paltry breath bearing up corpses, so that the tale of Dead Man's Land is clearer."

XXII. "The poet" (21): Euripides, frag. 898 (Nauck); compare Aeschylus, Danaides, frag. 44.

XXIV. "Plato" (23): Theaetetus, p. 174 D.

XXXIV. "The poet" (34): Homer, Iliad, vi. 147.

XXXIV. "Wood": A translation of ulh, "matter."

XXXVIII. "Rhetoric" (38): Rather "the gift of speech"; or perhaps the "decree" of the reasoning faculty.

BOOK XI V. "Cithaeron" (6): Oedipus utters this cry after discovering that he has fulfilled his awful doom, he was exposed on Cithaeron as an infant to die, and the cry implies that he wishes he had died there. Sophocles, Oedipus Tyrannus, 1391.

V. "New Comedy...," etc. C. has here strayed from the Greek rather widely. Translate: "and understand to what end the New Comedy was adopted, which by small degrees degenerated into a mere show of skill in mimicry." C. writes Comedia Vetus, Media, Nova. XII. "Phocion" (13): When about to be put to death he charged his son to bear no malice against the Athenians.

XXVIII. "My heart," etc. (31): From Homer, Odyssey ix. 413. "They will" From Hesiod, Opera et Dies, 184.

"Epictetus" Arr. i. II, 37.

XXX. "Cut down grapes" (35): Correct "ears of corn." "Epictetus"(36): Arr. 3, 22, 105.

GLOSSARY

This Glossary includes all proper names (excepting a few which are insignificant or unknown) and all obsolete or obscure words. ADRIANUS, or Hadrian (76-138 A. D.), 14th Roman Emperor.

Agrippa, M. Vipsanius (63-12 B.C.), a distinguished soldier under Augustus.

Alexander the Great, King of Macedonia, and Conqueror of the East, 356-323 B.C.

Antisthenes of Athens, founder of the sect of Cynic philosophers, and an opponent of Plato, 5th century B.C Antoninus Pius, 15th Roman Emperor, 138-161 AD. one of the best princes that ever mounted a throne.

Apathia: the Stoic ideal was calmness in all circumstance an insensibility to pain, and absence of all exaltation at, pleasure or good fortune.

Apelles, a famous painter of antiquity.

Apollonius of Alexandria, called Dyscolus, or the 'ill-tempered,' a great grammarian.

Aposteme, tumour, excrescence.

Archimedes of Syracuse 287-212 B.C., the most famous mathematician of antiquity.

Athos, a mountain promontory at the N. of the Aegean Sea.

Augustus, first Roman Emperor (ruled 31 B.C.-14 AD.).

Avoid, void.

BACCHIUS: there Were several persons of this name, and the one meant is perhaps the musician.

Brutus (1) the liberator of the Roman people from their kings, and (2) the murderer of Cæsar.

Both names were household words.

Cæsar, Caius, Julius, the Dictator and Conqueror.

Caieta, a town in Latium.

Camillus, a famous dictator in the early days of the Roman Republic.

Carnuntum, a town on the Danube in Upper Pannonia.

Cato, called of Utica, a Stoic who died by his own hand after the battle of Thapsus, 46 B.C. His name was proverbial for virtue and courage.

Cautelous, cautious.

Cecrops, first legendary King of Athens.

Charax, perhaps the priestly historian of that name, whose date is unknown, except that it must be later than Nero.

Chirurgeon, surgeon.

Chrysippus, 280-207 B.C., a Stoic philosopher, and the founder of Stoicism as a systematic philosophy.

Circus, the Circus Maximus at Rome, where games were held. There were four companies who contracted to provide horses, drivers, etc. These were called Factiones, and each had its distinguishing colour: russata (red), albata (white), veneta (blue), prasina (green). There was high rivalry between them, and riots and bloodshed not infrequently.

Cithaeron, a mountain range N. of Attica.

Comedy, ancient; a term applied to the Attic comedy of Aristophanes and his time, which criticised persons and politics, like a modern comic journal, such as Punck. See New Comedy.

Compendious, short.

Conceit, opinion.

Contentation, contentment.

Crates, a Cynic philosopher of the 4th century B.C.

Crœsus, King of Lydia, proverbial for wealth; he reigned 560-546 B.C.

Cynics, a school of philosophers, founded by Antisthenes. Their texts were a kind of caricature of Socraticism. Nothing was good but virtue, nothing bad but vice. The Cynics repudiated all civil and social claims, and attempted to return to what they called a state of nature. Many of them were very disgusting in their manners.

DEMETRIUS of Phalerum, an Athenian orator, statesman, philosopher, and poet. Born 345 B.C.

Democritus of Abdera (460-361 B.C.), celebrated as the 'laughing philosopher,' whose constant thought was 'What fools these mortals be.' He invented the Atomic Theory.

Dio of Syracuse, a disciple of Plato, and afterwards tyrant of Syracuse. Murdered 353 B.C.

Diogenes, the Cynic, born about 412 B.C., renowned for his rudeness and hardihood.

Diognetus, a painter.

Dispense with, put up with.

Dogmata, pithy sayings, or philosophical rules of life.

EMPEDOCLES of Agrigentum, fl. 5th century B.C., a philosopher, who first laid down that there were "four elements." He believed in the transmigration of souls, and the indestructibility of matter.

Epictetus, a famous Stoic philosopher. He was of Phrygia, at first a slave, then freedman, lame, poor, and contented. The work called Encheiridion was compiled by a pupil from his discourses.

Epicureans, a sect of philosophers founded by Epicurus, who "combined the physics of Democritus," i.e. the atomic theory, "with the ethics of Aristippus."

They proposed to live for happiness, but the word did not bear that coarse and vulgar sense originally which it soon took.

Epicurus of Samos, 342-270 B.C.

Lived at Athens in his "gardens," an urbane and kindly, if somewhat useless, life. His character was simple and temperate, and had none of the vice or indulgence which was afterwards associated with the name of Epicurean.

Eudoxus of Cnidus, a famous astronomer and physician of the 4th century B. C.

FATAL, fated.

Fortuit, chance (adj.).

Fronto, M. Cornelius, a rhetorician and pleader, made consul in 143 A.D. A number of his letters to M, Aur. and others are extant.

GRANUA, a tributary of the Danube.

HELICE, ancient capital city of Achaia, swallowed up by an earthquake, 373 B.C.

Helvidius Priscus, son-in-law of Thrasea Paetus, a noble man and a lover of liberty. He was banished by Nero, and put to death by Vespasian.

Heraclitus of Ephesus, who lived in the 6th century B.C. He wrote on philosophy and natural science.

Herculaneum, near Mount Vesuvius, buried by the eruption of 79 AD.

Hercules, p. 167, should be Apollo. See Muses.

Hiatus, gap.

Hipparchus of Bithynia, an astronomer of the 2nd century B.C., "The true father of astronomy."

Hippocrates of Cos, about 460-357 B.C. One of the most famous physicians of antiquity.

IDIOT, means merely the non-proficient in anything, the "layman," he who was not technically trained in any art, craft, or calling.

LEONNATUS, a distinguished general under Alexander the Great.

Lucilla, daughter of M. Aurelius, and wife of Verus, whom she survived.

MÆCENAS, a trusted adviser of Augustus, and a munificent patron of wits and literary men.

Maximus, Claudius, a Stoic philosopher.

Menippus, a Cynic philosopher.

Meteores, ta metewrologika, "high philosophy," used specially of astronomy and natural philosophy, which were bound up with other speculations.

Middle Comedy, something midway between the Old and New Comedy. See Comedy, Ancient, and New Comedy.

Middle things, Book 7, XXV. The Stoics divided all things into virtue, vice, and indifferent things; but as "indifferent" they regarded most of those things which the world regards as good or bad, such as wealth or poverty. Of these, some were "to be desired," some "to be rejected."

Muses, the nine deities who presided over various kinds of poesy, music, etc. Their leader was Apollo, one of whose titles is Musegetes, the Leader of the Muses.

NERVES, strings.

New Comedy, the Attic Comedy of Menander and his school, which criticised not persons but manners, like a modern comic opera. See Comedy, Ancient.

PALESTRA, wrestling school.

Pancratiast, competitor in the pancratium, a combined contest which comprised boxing and wrestling.

Parmularii, gladiators armed with a small round shield (parma).

Pheidias, the most famous sculptor of antiquity.

Philippus, founder of the Macedonian supremacy, and father of Alexander the Great.

Phocion, an Athenian general and statesman, a noble and high-minded man, 4th century B.C.

He was called by Demosthenes, "the pruner of my periods."

He was put to death by the State in 317, on a false suspicion, and left a message for his son "to bear no grudge against the Athenians."

Pine, torment.

Plato of Athens, 429-347 B.C. He used the dialectic method invented by his master Socrates.

He was, perhaps, as much poet as philosopher. He is generally identified with the Theory of Ideas, that things are what they are by participation with our eternal Idea. His "Commonwealth" was a kind of Utopia.

Platonics, followers of Plato.

Pompeii, near Mount Vesuvius, buried in the eruption of 79 A. D.

Pompeius, C. Pompeius Magnus, a very successful general at the end of the Roman Republic (106-48 B.C.).

Prestidigitator, juggler.

Pythagoras of Samos, a philosopher, scientist, and moralist of the 6th century B.C.

QUADI, a tribe of S. Germany.

M. Aurelius carried on war against them, and part of this book was written in the field.

RICTUS, gape, jaws.

Rusticus, Q. Junius, or Stoic philosopher, twice made consul by M. Aurelius.

SACRARY, shrine.

Salaminius, Book 7, XXXVII. Leon of Sala-mis. Socrates was ordered by the Thirty Tyrants to fetch him before them, and Socrates, at his own peril, refused.

Sarmatae, a tribe dwelling in Poland.

Sceletum, skeleton.

Sceptics, a school of philosophy founded by Pyrrho (4th century B.C.). He advocated "suspension of judgment," and taught the relativity of knowledge and impossibility of proof. The school is not unlike the Agnostic school.

Scipio, the name of two great soldiers, P. Corn. Scipio Africanus, conqueror of Hannibal, and P.

Corn. Sc. Afr. Minor, who came into the family by adoption, who destroyed Carthage.

Secutoriani (a word coined by C.), the Sececutores, light-armed gladiators, who were pitted against others with net and trident.

Sextus of Chaeronea, a Stoic philosopher, nephew of Plutarch.

Silly, simple, common.

Sinuessa, a town in Latium.

Socrates, an Athenian philosopher (469-399 B.C.), founder of the dialectic method. Put to death on a trumped-up charge by his countrymen.

Stint, limit (without implying niggardliness).

Stoics, a philosophic system founded by Zeno (4th century B.C.), and systematised by Chrysippus (3rd century B.C.). Their physical theory was a pantheistic materialism, their summum bonum "to live according to nature." Their wise man needs nothing, he is sufficient to himself; virtue is good, vice bad, external things indifferent.

THEOPHRASTUS, a philosopher, pupil of Aristotle, and his successor as president of the Lyceum. He wrote a large number of works on philosophy and natural history. Died 287 B.C.

Thrasea, P. Thrasea Pactus, a senator and Stoic philosopher, a noble and courageous man. He was condemned to death by Nero.

Tiberius, 2nd Roman Emperor (14-31 AD.). He spent the latter part of his life at Capreae (Capri), off Naples, in luxury or debauchery, neglecting his imperial duties.

To-torn, torn to pieces.

Trajan, 13th Roman Emperor, 52-117 A.D.

VERUS, Lucius Aurelius, colleague of M. Aurelius in the Empire.

He married Lucilla, daughter of M. A., and died 169 A.D.

Vespasian, 9th Roman Emperor XENOCRATES of Chalcedon, 396-314 B.C., a philosopher, and president of the Academy.

Paragraphs with First Lines

HIS FIRST BOOK

I. Of my grandfather Verus I have learned to be gentle and meek, and to

II. Of him that brought me up, not to be fondly addicted to either of

III. Of Diognetus, not to busy myself about vain things, and not easily

IV. To Rusticus I am beholding, that I first entered into the conceit

V. From Apollonius, true liberty, and unvariable steadfastness, and not

VI. Of Sextus, mildness and the pattern of a family governed with

VII. From Alexander the Grammarian, to be un-reprovable myself, and not

VIII. Of Fronto, to how much envy and fraud and hypocrisy the state of a

IX. Of Alexander the Platonic, not often nor without great necessity to

X. Of Catulus, not to contemn any friend's expostulation, though unjust,

XI. From my brother Severus, to be kind and loving to all them of my

XII. From Claudius Maximus, in all things to endeavour to have power

XIII. In my father, I observed his meekness; his constancy without

XIV. From the gods I received that I had good grandfathers, and parents,

XV. In the country of the Quadi at Granua, these. Betimes in the morning

XVI. Whatsoever I am, is either flesh, or life, or that which we

XVII. Whatsoever proceeds from the gods immediately, that any man will

THE SECOND BOOK

I. Remember how long thou hast already put off these things, and how

II. Let it be thy earnest and incessant care as a Roman and a man to

III. Do, soul, do; abuse and contemn thyself; yet a while and the time

IV. Why should any of these things that happen externally, so much

V. For not observing the state of another man's soul, scarce was ever

VI. These things thou must always have in mind: What is the nature

VII. Theophrastus, where he compares sin with sin (as after a vulgar

VIII. Whatsoever thou dost affect, whatsoever thou dost project, so do,

IX. Consider how quickly all things are dissolved and resolved: the

X. It is the part of a man endowed with a good understanding faculty, to

XI. Consider with thyself how man, and by what part of his, is joined

XII. If thou shouldst live three thousand, or as many as ten thousands

XIII. Remember that all is but opinion and conceit, for those things

XIV. A man's soul doth wrong and disrespect itself first and especially,

XV. The time of a man's life is as a point; the substance of it ever

THE THIRD BOOK

I. A man must not only consider how daily his life wasteth and

II. This also thou must observe, that whatsoever it is that naturally

III. Hippocrates having cured many sicknesses, fell sick himself and

IV. Spend not the remnant of thy days in thoughts and fancies concerning

V. Do nothing against thy will, nor contrary to the community, nor

VI. To be cheerful, and to stand in no need, either of other men's help

VII. If thou shalt find anything in this mortal life better than

VIII. Never esteem of anything as profitable, which shall ever constrain

IX. In the mind that is once truly disciplined and purged, thou canst

X. Use thine opinative faculty with all honour and respect, for in

XI. To these ever-present helps and mementoes, let one more be added,

XII. What is this, that now my fancy is set upon? of what things doth

XIII. If thou shalt intend that which is present, following the rule of

XIV. As physicians and chirurgeons have always their instruments ready

XV. Be not deceived; for thou shalt never live to read thy moral

XVI. To steal, to sow, to buy, to be at rest, to see what is to be done

XVII. To be capable of fancies and imaginations, is common to man and

THE FOURTH BOOK

I. That inward mistress part of man if it be in its own true natural

II. Let nothing be done rashly, and at random, but all things according

III. They seek for themselves private retiring

IV. If to understand and to be reasonable be common unto all men, then

V. As generation is, so also death, a secret of nature's wisdom: a

VI. Such and such things, from such and such causes, must of necessity

VII. Let opinion be taken away, and no man will think himself wronged.

VIII. Whatsoever doth happen in the world, doth happen justly, and so if

IX. Conceit no such things, as he that wrongeth thee conceiveth,

X. These two rules, thou must have always in a readiness. First, do

XI. Hast thou reason? I have. Why then makest thou not use of it? For if

XII. As a part hitherto thou hast had a particular subsistence: and now

XIII. Within ten days, if so happen, thou shalt be esteemed a god of

XIV. Not as though thou hadst thousands of years to live. Death hangs

XV. Now much time and leisure doth he gain, who is not curious to know

XVI. He who is greedy of credit and reputation after his death, doth

XVII. If so be that the souls remain after death (say they that will not

XVIII. Not to wander out of the way, but upon every motion and desire,

XIX. Whatsoever is expedient unto thee, O World, is expedient unto me;

XX. They will say commonly, Meddle not with many things, if thou wilt

XXI. Try also how a good man's life; (of one, who is well pleased with

XXII. Either this world is a kosmoz or comely piece, because all

XXIII. A black or malign disposition, an effeminate disposition; an

XXIV. He is a true fugitive, that flies from reason, by which men are

XXV. There is, who without so much as a coat; and there is, who without

XXVI. What art and profession soever thou hast learned, endeavour to

XXVII. Consider in my mind, for example's sake, the times of Vespasian:

XXVIII. Those words which once were common and ordinary, are now become

XXIX. Whatsoever is now present, and from day to day hath its existence;

XXX. Thou art now ready to die, and yet hast thou not attained to

XXXI. Behold and observe, what is the state of their rational part; and

XXXII. In another man's mind and understanding thy evil Cannot subsist,

XXXIII. Ever consider and think upon the world as being but one living

XXXIV. What art thou, that better and divine part excepted, but as

XXXV. To suffer change can be no hurt; as no benefit it is, by change to

XXXVI. Whatsoever doth happen in the world, is, in the course of nature,

XXXVII. Let that of Heraclitus never be out of thy mind, that the death

XXXVIII. Even as if any of the gods should tell thee, Thou shalt

XXXIX. Let it be thy perpetual meditation, how many physicians who

XL. Thou must be like a promontory of the sea, against which though

XLI. Oh, wretched I, to whom this mischance is happened! nay, happy I,

XLII. It is but an ordinary coarse one, yet it is a good effectual

XLIII. Let thy course ever be the most compendious way. The most

THE FIFTH BOOK

I. In the morning when thou findest thyself unwilling to rise, consider

II. How easy a thing is it for a man to put off from him all turbulent

III. Think thyself fit and worthy to speak, or to do anything that is

IV. I continue my course by actions according to nature, until I

V. No man can admire thee for thy sharp acute language, such is thy

VI. Such there be, who when they have done a good turn to any, are ready

VII. The form of the Athenians' prayer did run thus: 'O rain, rain, good

VIII. As we say commonly, The physician hath prescribed unto this man,

IX. Be not discontented, be not disheartened, be not out of hope, if

X. Thou must comfort thyself in the expectation of thy natural

XI. What is the use that now at this present I make of my soul? Thus

XII. What those things are in themselves, which by the greatest part are

XIII. All that I consist of, is either form or matter. No corruption can

XIV. Reason, and rational power, are faculties which content themselves

XV. Such as thy thoughts and ordinary cogitations are, such will thy

XVI. To desire things impossible is the part of a mad man. But it is a

XVII. After one consideration, man is nearest unto us; as we are bound

XVIII. Honour that which is chiefest and most powerful in the world, and

XIX. That which doth not hurt the city itself; cannot hurt any citizen.

XX. Let not that chief commanding part of thy soul be ever subject to

XXI. To live with the Gods. He liveth with the Gods, who at all times

XXII. Be not angry neither with him whose breath, neither with him whose

XXIII. 'Where there shall neither roarer be, nor harlot.' Why so? As

XXIV. That rational essence by which the universe is governed, is for

XXV. How hast thou carried thyself hitherto towards the Gods? towards

XXVI. Why should imprudent unlearned souls trouble that which is

XXVII. Within a very little while, thou wilt be either ashes, or a

XXVIII. Thou mayest always speed, if thou wilt but make choice of the

XXIX. If this neither be my wicked act, nor an act anyways depending

XXX. Let death surprise rue when it will, and where it will, I may be a

THE SIXTH BOOK

I. The matter itself, of which the universe doth consist, is of itself

II. Be it all one unto thee, whether half frozen or well warm; whether

III. Look in, let not either the proper quality, or the true worth of

IV. All substances come soon to their change, and either they shall

V. The best kind of revenge is, not to become like unto them.

VI. Let this be thy only joy, and thy only comfort, from one sociable

VII. The rational commanding part, as it alone can stir up and turn

VIII. According to the nature of the universe all things particular are

IX. Whensoever by some present hard occurrences thou art constrained to

X. If it were that thou hadst at one time both a stepmother, and

XI. How marvellous useful it is for a man to represent unto himself

XII. See what Crates pronounceth concerning Xenocrates himself.

XIII. Those things which the common sort of people do admire, are most

XIV. Some things hasten to be, and others to be no more. And even

XV. Not vegetative spiration, it is not surely (which plants have) that

XVI. Under, above, and about, are the motions of the elements; but

XVII. Who can choose but wonder at them? They will not speak well of

XVIII. Do not ever conceive anything impossible to man, which by thee

XIX. Suppose that at the palestra somebody hath all to-torn thee with

XX. If anybody shall reprove me, and shall make it apparent unto me,

XXI. I for my part will do what belongs unto me; as for other things,

XXII. Alexander of Macedon, and he that dressed his mules, when once

XXIII Consider how many different things, whether they concern our

XXIV. if any should put this question unto thee, how this word Antoninus

XXV. Is it not a cruel thing to forbid men to affect those things, which

XXVI. Death is a cessation from the impression of the senses, the

XXVII. If in this kind of life thy body be able to hold out, it is a

XXVIII. Do all things as becometh the disciple of Antoninus Pius.

XXIX. Stir up thy mind, and recall thy wits again from thy natural

XXX. I consist of body and soul. Unto my body all things are

XXXI. As long as the foot doth that which belongeth unto it to do, and

XXXII. Dost thou not see, how even those that profess mechanic arts,

XXXIII. Asia, Europe; what are they, but as corners of the whole world;

XXXIV He that seeth the things that are now, hath Seen all that either

XXXV. Fit and accommodate thyself to that estate and to those

XXXVI. What things soever are not within the proper power and

XXXVII. We all work to one effect, some willingly, and with a rational

XXXVIII. Doth either the sun take upon him to do that which belongs to

XXXIX. If so be that the Gods have deliberated in particular of those

XL. Whatsoever in any kind doth happen to any one, is expedient to the

XLI. As the ordinary shows of the theatre and of other such places,

XLII. Let the several deaths of men of all sorts, and of all sorts of

XLIII. When thou wilt comfort and cheer thyself, call to mind the

XLIV. Dost thou grieve that thou dost weigh but so many pounds, and not

XLV. Let us do our best endeavours to persuade them; but however, if

XLVI. The ambitious supposeth another man's act, praise and applause, to

XLVII. It is in thy power absolutely to exclude all manner of conceit

XLVIII. Use thyself when any man speaks unto thee, so to hearken unto

XLIX. That which is not good for the bee-hive, cannot be good for the

L. Will either passengers, or patients, find fault and complain, either

LI. How many of them who came into the world at the same time when I

LII. To them that are sick of the jaundice, honey seems bitter; and to

LIII. No man can hinder thee to live as thy nature doth require. Nothing

LIV. What manner of men they be whom they seek to please, and what to

THE SEVENTH BOOK

I. What is wickedness? It is that which many time and often thou hast

II. What fear is there that thy dogmata, or philosophical resolutions

III. That which most men would think themselves most happy for, and

IV. Word after word, every one by itself, must the things that are

V. Is my reason, and understanding sufficient for this, or no? If it be

VI. Let not things future trouble thee. For if necessity so require that

VII. Whatsoever is material, doth soon vanish away into the common

VIII. To a reasonable creature, the same action is both according

IX. Straight of itself, not made straight.

X. As several members in one body united, so are reasonable creatures

XI. Of things that are external, happen what will to that which can

XII. Whatsoever any man either doth or saith, thou must be good; not for

XIII. This may ever be my comfort and security: my understanding, that

XIV. What is rv&nfLovia, or happiness: but a7~o~ &d~wv, or, a good

XV. Is any man so foolish as to fear change, to which all things that

XVI. Through the substance of the universe, as through a torrent pass

XVII. The nature of the universe, of the common substance of all things

XVIII. An angry countenance is much against nature, and it is oftentimes

XIX. Whensoever any man doth trespass against other, presently consider

XX. Fancy not to thyself things future, as though they were present

XXI. Wipe off all opinion stay the force and violence of unreasonable

XXII. All things (saith he) are by certain order and appointment. And

XXIII. Out of Plato. 'He then whose mind is endowed with true

XXIV. Out of Antisthenes. 'It is a princely thing to do well, and to be

XXV. Out of several poets and comics. 'It will but little avail thee,

XXVI. Out of Plato. 'My answer, full of justice and equity, should be

XXVII. To look back upon things of former ages, as upon the manifold

XXVIII. He hath a stronger body, and is a better wrestler than I. What

XXIX. Where the matter may be effected agreeably to that reason, which

XXX. Look not about upon other men's minds and understandings; but look

XXXI. As one who had lived, and were now to die by right, whatsoever is

XXXII. Thou must use thyself also to keep thy body fixed and steady;

XXXIII. The art of true living in this world is more like a wrestler's,

XXXIV. Thou must continually ponder and consider with thyself, what

XXXV. What pain soever thou art in, let this presently come to thy mind,

XXXVI. Take heed lest at any time thou stand so affected, though towards

XXXVII. How know we whether Socrates were so eminent indeed, and of so

XXXVIII. For it is a thing very possible, that a man should be a very

XXXIX. Free from all compulsion in all cheerfulness and alacrity thou

XL. Then hath a man attained to the estate of perfection in his life and

XLI. Can the Gods, who are immortal, for the continuance of so many ages

XLII. What object soever, our reasonable and sociable faculty doth meet

XLIII. When thou hast done well, and another is benefited by thy action,

XLIV. The nature of the universe did once certainly before it was

THE EIGHTH BOOK

I. This also, among other things, may serve to keep thee from vainglory;

II. Upon every action that thou art about, put this question to thyself;

III. Alexander, Caius, Pompeius; what are these to Diogenes, Heraclitus,

IV. What they have done, they will still do, although thou shouldst hang

V. That which the nature of the universe doth busy herself about, is;

VI. Every particular nature hath content, when in its own proper course

VII. Thou hast no time nor opportunity to read. What then? Hast thou

VIII. Forbear henceforth to complain of the trouble of a courtly life,

IX. Repentance is an inward and self-reprehension for the neglect or

X. This, what is it in itself, and by itself, according to its proper

XI. When thou art hard to be stirred up and awaked out of thy sleep,

XII. As every fancy and imagination presents itself unto thee, consider

XIII. At thy first encounter with any one, say presently to thyself:

XIV. Remember, that to change thy mind upon occasion, and to follow him

XV. If it were thine act and in thine own power, wouldest thou do

XVI. Whatsoever dieth and falleth, however and wheresoever it die

XVII. Whatsoever is, was made for something: as a horse, a vine. Why

XVIII. Nature hath its end as well in the end and final consummation of

XIX. As one that tosseth up a ball. And what is a ball the better, if

XX. That which must be the subject of thy consideration, is either the

XXI. Most justly have these things happened unto thee: why dost not

XXII. Shall I do it? I will; so the end of my action be to do good unto

XXIII. By one action judge of the rest: this bathing which usually takes

XXIV. Lucilla buried Verus; then was Lucilla herself buried by others.

XXV. The true joy of a man, is to do that which properly belongs unto a

XXVI. If pain be an evil, either it is in regard of the body; (and that

XXVII. Wipe off all idle fancies, and say unto thyself incessantly; Now

XXVIII. Whether thou speak in the Senate or whether thou speak to any

XXIX. Augustus his court; his wife, his daughter, his nephews, his

XXX. Contract thy whole life to the measure and proportion of one single

XXXI. Receive temporal blessings without ostentation, when they are sent

XXXII. If ever thou sawest either a hand, or a foot, or a head lying by

XXXIII. As almost all her other faculties and properties the nature of

XXXIV. Let not the general representation unto thyself of the

XXXV. What? are either Panthea or Pergamus abiding to this day by their

XXXVI. If thou beest quick-sighted, be so in matter of judgment, and

XXXVII. In the whole constitution of man, I see not any virtue contrary

XXXVIII. If thou canst but withdraw conceit and opinion concerning that

XXXIX. That which is a hindrance of the senses, is an evil to the

XL. If once round and solid, there is no fear that ever it will change.

XLI. Why should I grieve myself; who never did willingly grieve any

XLII. This time that is now present, bestow thou upon thyself. They that

XLIII. Take me and throw me where thou wilt: I am indifferent. For there

XLIV. Is this then a thing of that worth, that for it my soul should

XLV. Nothing can happen unto thee, which is not incidental unto thee, as

XLVI. Remember that thy mind is of that nature as that it becometh

XLVII. Keep thyself to the first bare and naked apprehensions of things,

XLVIII. Is the cucumber bitter? set it away. Brambles are in the way?

XLIX. Not to be slack and negligent; or loose, and wanton in thy

L. 'They kill me, they cut my flesh; they persecute my person with

LI. He that knoweth not what the world is, knoweth not where he himself

LII. Not only now henceforth to have a common breath, or to hold

LIII. Wickedness in general doth not hurt the world. Particular

LIV. The sun seemeth to be shed abroad. And indeed it is diffused but

LV. He that feareth death, either feareth that he shall have no sense at

LVI. All men are made one for another: either then teach them better, or

LVII. The motion of the mind is not as the motion of a dart. For

LVIII. To pierce and penetrate into the estate of every one's

THE NINTH BOOK

I. He that is unjust, is also impious. For the nature of the universe,

II. It were indeed more happy and comfortable, for a man to depart out

III. Thou must not in matter of death carry thyself scornfully, but as

IV. He that sinneth, sinneth unto himself. He that is unjust, hurts

V. If my present apprehension of the object be right, and my present

VI. To wipe away fancy, to use deliberation, to quench concupiscence, to

VII. Of all unreasonable creatures, there is but one unreasonable soul;

VIII. Man, God, the world, every one in their kind, bear some fruits.

IX. Either teach them better if it be in thy power; or if it be not,

X. Labour not as one to whom it is appointed to be wretched, nor as one

XI. This day I did come out of all my trouble. Nay I have cast out all

XII. All those things, for matter of experience are usual and ordinary;

XIII. The things themselves that affect us, they stand without doors,

XIV. As virtue and wickedness consist not in passion, but in action; so

XV. To the stone that is cast up, when it comes down it is no hurt unto

XVI. Sift their minds and understandings, and behold what men they be,

XVII. All things that are in the world, are always in the estate

XVIII. it is not thine, but another man's sin. Why should it trouble

XIX. Of an operation and of a purpose there is an ending, or of an

XX. As occasion shall require, either to thine own understanding, or to

XXI. As thou thyself, whoever thou art, were made for the perfection and

XXII. Children's anger, mere babels; wretched souls bearing up dead

XXIII. Go to the quality of the cause from which the effect doth

XXIV. Infinite are the troubles and miseries, that thou hast already

XXV. When any shall either impeach thee with false accusations, or

XXVI. Up and down, from one age to another, go the ordinary things of

XXVII. Within a while the earth shall cover us all, and then she herself

XXVIII. And these your professed politicians, the only true practical

XXIX. From some high place as it were to look down, and to behold

XXX. Many of those things that trouble and straiten thee, it is in thy

XXXI. To comprehend the whole world together in thy mind, and the whole

XXXII. What are their minds and understandings; and what the things that

XXXIII. Loss and corruption, is in very deed nothing else but change and

XXXIV. How base and putrid, every common matter is! Water, dust, and

XXXV. Will this querulousness, this murmuring, this complaining and

XXXVI. It is all one to see these things for a hundred of years together

XXXVII. If he have sinned, his is the harm, not mine. But perchance he

XXXVIII. Either all things by the providence of reason happen unto every

XXXIX. Sayest thou unto that rational part, Thou art dead; corruption

XL. Either the Gods can do nothing for us at all, or they can still and

XLI. 'In my sickness' (saith Epicurus of himself:) 'my discourses were

XLII. It is common to all trades and professions to mind and intend that

XLIII. When at any time thou art offended with any one's impudency, put

THE TENTH BOOK

I. O my soul, the time I trust will be, when thou shalt be good, simple,

II. As one who is altogether governed by nature, let it be thy care to

III. Whatsoever doth happen unto thee, thou art naturally by thy natural

IV. Him that offends, to teach with love and meek ness, and to show him

V. Whatsoever it be that happens unto thee, it is that which from all

VI. Either with Epicurus, we must fondly imagine the atoms to be the

VII. All parts of the world, (all things I mean that are contained

VIII. Now that thou hast taken these names upon thee of good, modest,

IX. Toys and fooleries at home, wars abroad: sometimes terror, sometimes

X. As the spider, when it hath caught the fly that it hunted after, is

XI. To find out, and set to thyself some certain way and method of

XII. He hath got loose from the bonds of his body, and perceiving that

XIII. What use is there of suspicion at all? or, why should thoughts

XIV. What is that that is slow, and yet quick? merry, and yet grave? He

XV. In the morning as soon as thou art awaked, when thy judgment, before

XVI. Give what thou wilt, and take away what thou wilt, saith he that is

XVII. So live as indifferent to the world and all worldly objects, as

XVIII. Make it not any longer a matter of dispute or discourse, what are

XIX. Ever to represent unto thyself; and to set before thee, both the

XX. Consider them through all actions and occupations, of their lives:

XXI. That is best for every one, that the common nature of all doth send

XXII. The earth, saith the poet, doth often long after the rain. So is

XXIII. Either thou dost Continue in this kind of life and that is it,

XXIV Let it always appear and be manifest unto thee that solitariness,

XXV. He that runs away from his master is a fugitive. But the law is

XXVI. From man is the seed, that once cast into the womb man hath no

XXVII. Ever to mind and consider with thyself; how all things that now

XXVIII. As a pig that cries and flings when his throat is cut, fancy to

XXIX. Whatsoever it is that thou goest about, consider of it by thyself,

XXX. When thou art offended with any man's transgression, presently

XXXI. When thou seest Satyro, think of Socraticus and Eutyches, or

XXXII. What a subject, and what a course of life is it, that thou doest

XXXIII. Let it not be in any man's power, to say truly of thee, that

XXXIV. As he that is bitten by a mad dog, is afraid of everything almost

XXXV. A good eye must be good to see whatsoever is to be seen, and not

XXXVI. There is not any man that is so happy in his death, but that some

XXXVII. Use thyself; as often, as thou seest any man do anything,

XXXVIII. Remember, that that which sets a man at work, and hath power

THE ELEVENTH BOOK

I. The natural properties, and privileges of a reasonable soul are: That

II. A pleasant song or dance; the Pancratiast's exercise, sports that

III. That soul which is ever ready, even now presently (if need be) from

IV. Have I done anything charitably? then am I benefited by it. See

V. Tragedies were at first brought in and instituted, to put men in mind

VI. How clearly doth it appear unto thee, that no other course of thy

VII. A branch cut off from the continuity of that which was next unto

VIII. To grow together like fellow branches in matter of good

IX. It is not possible that any nature should be inferior unto art,

X. The things themselves (which either to get or to avoid thou art put

XI. Then is the soul as Empedocles doth liken it, like unto a sphere or

XII. Will any contemn me? let him look to that, upon what grounds he

XIII. They contemn one another, and yet they seek to please one another:

XIV. How rotten and insincere is he, that saith, I am resolved to carry

XV. To live happily is an inward power of the soul, when she is affected

XVI. Of everything thou must consider from whence it came, of what

XVII. Four several dispositions or inclinations there be of the mind and

XVIII. What portion soever, either of air or fire there be in thee,

XIX. He that hath not one and the self-same general end always as long

XX. Remember the fable of the country mouse and the city mouse, and the

XXI. Socrates was wont to call the common conceits and opinions of men,

XXII. The Lacedæmonians at their public spectacles were wont to appoint

XXIII. What Socrates answered unto Perdiccas, why he did not come unto

XXIV. In the ancient mystical letters of the Ephesians, there was an

XXV. The Pythagoreans were wont betimes in the morning the first thing

XXVI. How Socrates looked, when he was fain to gird himself with a

XXVII. In matter of writing or reading thou must needs be taught before

XXVIII. 'My heart smiled within me.' 'They will accuse even virtue

XXIX. As they that long after figs in winter when they cannot be had; so

XXX. 'As often as a father kisseth his child, he should say secretly

XXXI. 'Of the free will there is no thief or robber:' out of Epictetus;

THE TWELFTH BOOK

I. Whatsoever thou doest hereafter aspire unto, thou mayest even now

II. God beholds our minds and understandings, bare and naked from these

III. I have often wondered how it should come to pass, that every man

IV. how come it to pass that the Gods having ordered all other things

V. Use thyself even unto those things that thou doest at first despair

VI. Let these be the objects of thy ordinary meditation: to consider,

VII. All worldly things thou must behold and consider, dividing them

VIII. How happy is man in this his power that hath been granted unto

IX. Whatsoever doth happen in the ordinary course and consequence of

X. How ridiculous and strange is he, that wonders at anything that

XI. Either fate, (and that either an absolute necessity, and unavoidable

XII. At the conceit and apprehension that such and such a one hath

XIII. If it be not fitting, do it not. If it be not true, speak it not.

XIV. Of everything that presents itself unto thee, to consider what the

XV. It is high time for thee, to understand that there is somewhat in

XVI. Remember that all is but opinion, and all opinion depends of the

XVII. No operation whatsoever it he, ceasing for a while, can be truly

XVIII. These three things thou must have always in a readiness: first

XIX. Cast away from thee opinion, and thou art safe. And what is it that

XX. Let thy thoughts ever run upon them, who once for some one thing or

XXI. To them that ask thee, Where hast thou seen the Gods, or how

XXII. Herein doth consist happiness of life, for a man to know

XXIII. There is but one light of the sun, though it be intercepted by

XXIV. What doest thou desire? To live long. What? To enjoy the

XXV. What a small portion of vast and infinite eternity it is, that is

XXVI. What is the present estate of my understanding? For herein lieth

XXVII. To stir up a man to the contempt of death this among other